Dr. Darrell Clayton Crain Jr. P035
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Dr. Darrell Clayton Crain Jr. Photograph Collection
1949-1989
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Crain, Darrell Clayton, Jr., Dr.
P035
2 boxes
Biographical / Historical
Native Washingtonian and lifelong resident of Washington, D.C., Dr. Darrell Clayton Crain Jr. (1910-1995) dedicated 50 years of his life to the practice of medicine. After graduating from the George Washington University School of Medicine and completing residency at Emergency Hospital, Dr. Crain served as Medical Officer at Walter Reed General Hospital before entering private practice in 1937. Notable achievements in his field include co-founding the Arthritis Rehabilitation Center in Washington, founding of the Rheumatology Clinic at Georgetown University Hospital, serving in professional and civic societies, and writing several books. Dr. Crain was a rheumatologist by profession and photographer by hobby. While in his home of Washington, D.C. and traveling the country and abroad, he documented his experiences on film, leaving behind vibrant, color photographs that give a vivid glimpse of the past. From family vacations to the aftermath of the 1968 riots in Washington, D.C. to professional travel in Monaco, Dr. Crain captured candid and intimate historical moments over the span of four decades.
Custodial History
The Dr. Darrell C. Crain Jr. Photograph Collection was donated to the Library by Barbara Crain Rollinson and Alice R. Makl, daughter and granddaughter of the late Dr. Crain on June 2, 2015.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of 270 Kodachrome Ektachrome slides, 3 empty slide boxes, and one original 8x10 black and white photograph, as well as 275 digital surrogates of all of the analog images donated and several family photographs of Crain and his homes which the library only received digitally. The photographs document daily life in the Washington, DC area, Dr. Crain's travels around the U.S. and abroad, and important events. Events depicted include the March on Washington, the Resurrection City protests, the 1776 United States bicentennial celebration, 1965 and 1977 presidential inauguration parades, and the aftermath of the 1968 riots. Sites photographed around the Washington area include Glen Echo Park, Georgetown University and Georgetown University Hospital, the Tidal Basin during Cherry Blossom season, the National Mall, 14th Street, Northminster Presbyterian Church, and other sites and statues around D.C. Locations of photography outside of Washington include Duke University, Nevada, Hershey, Pennsylvania, Chatham, Massachusetts, Maine, Upstate New York, Vermont, Death Valley, the western United States, Bermuda and Monaco.
Civil rights; Photographs
- Series 1
  - Tidal Basin Cherry Blossoms, 1949 April (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Children's Day at Northminster Presbyterian Church, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Glen Echo Park Crystal Pool, June 1950 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Christmas - Georgetown University Hospital, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Georgetown University Construction of St. Mary's Hall, 1955-1958 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Duke University Homecoming - Durham - North Carolina, October 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Cherry Blossoms and Easter Monday - Tidal Basin and White House, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Nevada /Las Vegas/Hoover Dam, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bermuda/Hamilton/various other locations, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Civil Rights March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom, August 28 1963 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Inauguration Parade for President Lyndon Johnson, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hotel Hershey in Hershey - Pennsylvania, June 1965 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Razing Stoneleigh Court Apartments - Connecticut Ave. NW, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Big Snow, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tents in Lafayette Square, April 1966 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Western USA - Utah and Colorado, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Aftermath of DC Riots following assassination of Martin Luther King, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Resurrection City and Solidarity Day, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Monaco, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - New Orleans (Jackson Square and French Quarter), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Bicentennial Fireworks on the National Mall, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chatham - Massachusetts, August 1976 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Inauguration Parade for President Jimmy Carter, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Maine and Upstate NY (Bar Harbor -Maine/Ausable Chasm - NY/Mirror Lake - NY), 1977 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Death Valley National Park - California, March 1978 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Vermont (Plymouth and Woodstock - Vermont), October 1988 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Statuary in Washington DC, January 1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Residences of Dr. Darrell C. Crain Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Scope and Contents
    (digital only for 1919, 1926, and 1941 images)
  - One 8x10 black and white photograph taken in the living room of Dr. Crain's home at 1619 Roxanna Road NW Washington D.C. during an organizational meeting of the DC Rheumatism Society, June 4 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)